Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin 1777 January-1778 March Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 2 -- Letters to Franklin
1777 January-1778 March
Mss.B.F85inventory02
American Philosophical Society
1.0 section
This is part of the large inventory for the Benjamin Franklin Papers (Mss B F85). For complete information concerning this collection, please view the Collection Description.
Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
- Letters to Benjamin Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 1; A.L.S. 1p.; Thornton, E. Paris
    Scope and Contents note
    Enclosing a letter to Franklin and requesting an acknowledgement of same.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 2; D.S. John Hancock, with seal. 1p.; The Continental Congress. Baltimore
    Commission of Benjamin Franklin as Commissioner to the Court of Spain.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 2; L.S. 1p.; Duportail, Louis Le Bègue. Versailles
    Requesting Franklin to send him a reply with reference to his proposition relating to a corps of troops.
    (In French.)
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 3; L.S. 3p.; Lutterloh, Major Henry Emanuel. Paris
    Giving particulars about himself and his previous services. Secrecy of his mission to Paris. His offer to raise troops in Germany or Northern Europe.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 4; A.L.S.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Surprised to hear of Franklin's arrival in Paris; hopes his coming has for its object a happy reunion between the mother country and her colonies. If he had known earlier of Franklin's arrival would have accompanied his Imperial master to France; Franklin will probably see and talk with him in the disguise of a private man. Proposes various schemes to enable him to come to Paris, one of them, the desire on the part of some family of distinction there to have him inoculate their children.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 4; L.S.; Wickes, Lambert. Nantes
    Acknowledging his favor of 26th December; will immediately proceed to Port I'Orient and execute that business; will come to Paris on his return, if Franklin thinks it absolutely necessary.
  - to The Deputies [American Commissioners]., 1777 January 6; L. 1p.; Gérard, Conrad Alexandre. Versailles
    Desires them to postpone the communication of the memorial containing particular requests. Will advise them when it can be opportunely presented; might confine themselves for the present to the memorial explaining the state of affairs in America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 7; A.L.S. 1p.; Ferry, Jeremiah. Paris
    His principal business in Paris is to get a more satisfactory account of his countrymen in America than he has been able to do in England, for which purpose he will wait on Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777, January 8; A.L.S.1p.; Terry, Jeremiah. Paris
    Asks for half an hour's private conversation with Franklin's previous to his departure for London; will also be glad of Mr. Deane's acquaintance.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 8; L. in 3d P. 1p.; Lutterloh, Major H. E. Paris
    With reference to his proposal to raise a corps of troops in Germany for service in the United States.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 8; A.L.S. 2p.; Lutterloh, Major H. E. Paris
    Plans and conditions under which he will enter the American Army.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 8; N. in 3d P. 1p.; Dalibard, Thomas François
    Introducing M. de Roussille who wishes to confer with Dr. Franklin about some expeditions he proposes to make in North America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 9; Memp. 4p.; The Farmers-General. Paris
    Memorandum with reference to shipments of tobacco to be made to the Farmers-General by Messrs. Franklin, Deane and Lee for account of Congress. Questions and replies as to terms, manner of shipment and delivery, payment, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 9; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, William Temple. Passy
    News received from Mr. Montaudouin of the arrival of a Scotchman at Nantes who says Gen. Howe had embarked ten thousand men to attack Philadelphia; Montaudouin also mentioned an unexpected meeting he had with Du Coudray, who sailed from Havre December 14.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 9; L.S. Benj. Harrison, Richard Henry Lee. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Secret Committee. Baltimore
    Minute account of Gen. Washington's movements against the enemy at Trenton and Princeton, and the numbers captured and slain; this information gathered from a gentleman who was in the action; supposes the General has been too busy to write and waits the final issue.
    Bibliography
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 97.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 9; A.L.S. 1p.; Chaumont, Jacques-Donatien Le Ray de
    Can procure 200,000 pounds of East India salt-petre at 60 livres the hundredweight; asks for a prompt decision.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 10; A.L.S. 2p.; Rumsey, Nathan. Nantes
    Jealousy between the Admiralty officers of Vannes and M. Guérin of Auray about the latter's having ventured on such a purchase without their consent, and they seem determined to give as much trouble as possible; hopes Franklin can prevail with the marine officers to order those officers of Vannes to desist troubling M. Guérin as if these matters are carried too far they may injure the sales of our prizes hereafter.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 10; A.L.S. 4p.; Gloro, ------. L'Orient
    Asks if Franklin knows anything of one Benjamin Salter; tells of a transaction he had with him at the Ascension Isles; he sold him goods and received in payment two bills of exchange; one of them drawn on William Carothorne in London, who is a prisoner for debt in the King's Exchange prison and will say nothing to it. His desperate financial difficulties.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 10; A.L.S. 3p.; de Vallenais,-----. Paris
    M. de Chaumont's ship, in which he was to embark, has lately set sail. Several others ready to set sail in two or three weeks. Asks for a letter to Mr. Grouet so that he may treat with him for their passage on them to America; will take a relation along with him; their intention not only to get in the American service, but to settle for life in that free country.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 11; A.L.S. 3p.; Wickes, Lambert. Nantes
    Has no opinion of the 60-gun ship; thinks the frigates better for his purpose. Recommends the St. John. Can get other ships but fears they are too ancient.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 12; A.L.S. 3p.; Ritchie, Juliana. Cambray
    Warns Franklin that he is surrounded by spies who watch his every movement; motive for this espionage. She resides at present at Cambray, taking charge of five young ladies of fortune. Her great friendship for Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 13; A.L.S. 2p.; Blondel de Lantone (de Moulins), -----. Moulinnes
    His sympathy with the Bostonians in their revolt against tyranny. Served for eight years in the King's guard, but after their disbandment has been unable to find a military opening. Asks Franklin to obtain for him a position in the American army suitable to an officer of his experience.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 13; A.L.S. 4p.; Kováts, Michaël. Bordeaux
    Details experience as private and officer in Hungary, and states that he is sailing from Bordeaux [for America]. Asks assistance for himself and friends.
    (In Latin.)
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 14; L. S. Rob[er]t Morris, Chairman. 2p.; The Continental Congress, Committee on Secret Correspondence. Philadelphia
    Transmit resolves of Congress of the 19th and 29th of November, last, relative to the purchase of supplies in France.
    Printed in Diplom. Corres., Wharton, II, 246.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 14; A.L.S. Rob[er]t Morris, Chairman. 3p.; The Continental Congress, Secret Committee. Philadelphia
    Enclosing two resolves of Congress concerning the purchase of brass cannon, arms and equipage. Disposition of the Court of France as regards their views.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Rumsey, Nathan. Nantes
    Has put the papers respecting the prizes in Mr. Morris's hands. Concerning Capt. Cod's offer to purchase his vessel of Capt. Wickes.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 14; L.S. 2p.; Richemond, Meschinet de, —, fils. La Rochelle
    Begging Franklin to send some American traders to La Rochelle; its fine haven and its excellent market; their brandy almost as good as that of Cognac.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 14; A.L.S.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    His arrival in Nantes; has been seen M. Montaudouin and Mr. Schweighauser; will collect the best information on every subject affecting American interests; will send a proper report later. Capt. Wickes waiting to know if prizes are admissible into French ports.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 14; A.L.S. 2p.; Fadeville, -----. Bordeaux
    Sends a letter written by a late major of a regiment of Hussars with the King of Prussia; he sails for America on the Catharine of Dartmouth; if some Prussian officers he expects fail to arrive before he sails, desires to know what steps he must take to enable them to follow.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 14; A.L.S .4p.; Wickes, Lambert. Nantes
    Concerning Captain Nicholson; advisability of having his assistance in Paris; his qualifications as a commander of a ship of war.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 112.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Guérin, -----. Paris
    Concerning the affair of his brother and the Admiralty officers.
    General note
    [See V, 9.]
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 15; A.L.S. 2p.; Ternant, Jean de. Bordeaux
    Just arrived in Bordeaux after a dangerous illness; his hasty departure renders doubtful the receipt of the letters Franklin promised him; has left directions for forwarding them. The new Spanish Minister, Count Florida Blanca, will undoubtedly serve his cause with unremitting ardor.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 16; A. L. 1p.; Le Bègue Louis, Duportail. Versailles
    He asks to know, as soon as possible, the result of his application.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 17; A.L.S. 1p.; D'Anmours, Chevalier. Bordeaux
    Received from Madame la Marquise de Saineville a letter written by Franklin in his favor to Mr. Morris in Philadelphia; sentiments of gratitude and veneration towards Franklin.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 17; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Description of the ship Mercury; her cargo, time of sailing, etc.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Enclosing a letter which he leaves to Franklin's judgement whether to send or not.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; MacDonald, Charles-Edouard-Frédéric-Henry, comte de. Pau
    Wishes to know that encouragement he can give to capable officers who offer their services to the United Provinces; his character well-known; originally from Scotland, now settled in France. Criticises the American tactics so far; has a plan of operation for America.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 18; Mem. 3p.; Macdonald, Comte. Pau
    His service and his plan of discipline for training soldiers, if his services are accepted by Congress.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Pecholier, Frères. Bordeaux
    Forwarding a letter from M. Ternant who left Bordeaux on the 15th; will forward him any letters from Franklin with great care.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 18; A.L.S. 1p.; Echlin, Henry. Prison of the Abbaie St. Germain
    Not personally known to Franklin, but ventures to address him, not as a countryman but as a fellow creature reduced by a captivity of nearly three years, by illness and every sort of evil, to the last degree of unhappiness. Was once a lover of liberty and an enemy to oppression. The bearer will receive Franklin's commands.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 18; A.L.S. 2p.; Wickes, Lambert. Nantes
    Enclosing a letter and an inventory of the frigate Count de Maurepas; concerning the fitting out of the ship; recommends Mr. Gourlade for this service.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 19; A.L. 2p.; Le Bègue Duportail, Louis. Paris
    Because he does not know sufficient English to read it when written, he is not sure that he has understood the answer sent to him at Versailles. As his friend, who understands English, is away, he writes that he thinks his request to enter the American service has been refused. If this is correct no answer is necessary; but, if he has misunderstood, he asks the answer to be written in Latin or French. Requests that all letters and writings from him be destroyed.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 21; A.L. 1p.; Le Bègue Duportail, Louis. Paris
    He is very sorry to have understood exactly the opposite to what was written. He will leave that evening for Versailles to learn the Minister's intention. He will write also to 'our gentlemen' to know their decision, then he will give their names.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Lutterloh, Major H. E. Paris
    He proposes another plan for recruiting; if it is not approved of, he goes to Nantes as agreed upon.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 21; A.L.S. 5p.; Dumas, Charles-Guillaume-Frédéric
    Business relative to his position as American agent; quotes certain correspondence he has had with a great commercial house.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 21; A.L. 3p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, Jacques. Paris
    Concerning the affair of supplying tobacco to the Farmers-General; formation for this purpose of a society, the result of which he hopes will be a market for commodities and merchandise, to the mutual advantage of two nations, and also to the individual members.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Finished the examination of the Mercury's cargo; other matters still to be attended to. Arrival of the Chevalier Duplessis; will do all he can to assist him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 21; A.L.S. 1p.; Montaudoüin de la Touche, Jean-Gabriel. Nantes
    Recommending to Franklin's notice M. de L'Ehombe, member of the Superior Council of Port au Prince; his keen desire to meet Franklin.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 21; A.L.S. 2p.; Buat, —, marquis de. Ploermel
    Desire of Chevalier de Louvigny and Chevalier le Fer to enter into the service of America. Wishes to know what treatment they would have if they entered the army, one as colonel, the other as captain of infantry or cavalry, and what advance money they would receive at the moment of departure.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Strahan, William. London
    Asking about Franklin's welfare. Sees Sir John Pringle often; he is quite well, barring insomnia. Hopes that peace, unity and happiness may be soon restored. Hears Franklin saw his colleague, Mr. Charles Fox, frequently; he will find him one of the cleverest fellows of his years he ever knew.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 23; A.L.S. 1p.; Paulze, Jacques. Paris
    Sees no difficulty in the matter of Mr. Franklin's taking an interest in the Society for furnishing tobacco to the Farmers-General.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 23; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Date of the Mercury's sailing; unless he receives further commands, will then set off for Paris. Trusts the Amphitrite got off from L'Orient.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 23; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Barbeu-Dubourg, -----
    Requesting Messrs. Franklin, Deane and Lee to give an interview to M. Bayard, on important business.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 Januray 24; D.S. 1p.; Pfeffinger, Jo. et al. Strassburg
    Attesting the wholesomeness of a beverage similar to beer, manufactured by Anton Holper and Frantz Xaverius Deck, in Landsor, upper Alsace.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 24; A.L.S. 4p.; Captain Garanger, Havre
    Has a letter of recommendation to Franklin from M. Brisson; his twenty-one years' service in the artillery; his desire to enter the service of America; his friends obtained for him from the King the rank of captain of artillery and for his brother that of lieutenant; only expected to wait at Havre six days, and it is now six weeks; their money exhausted, have received no advance on their appointments; asks Franklin's assistance.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 25; A.L. 2p.; Le Bègue Duportail, Louis. Paris
    The Court permits him to carry out his plan. Because of this voyage and to recompense him for a great work for the corps, just terminated, he is given the title of Lieutenant Colonel of the Royal Engineer Corps. His first condition for entering the American service was that he should have a rank higher than he held in France at the moment of leaving. He makes the same request for his companions, M. de Laumoy and M. de Gouvion. He urges great caution in making inquires about these two. If these conditions are accepted he will come immediately to make the final arrangements.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 Janaury 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Sarsfield, Guy-Claude, comte de
    Will always remember his meeting with Franklin in London some years ago; expects to be in Paris in a few weeks and will wait upon him; in the meantime recommends to Franklin's notice his brother, who is also, his best friend.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 25; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Treated like the nephew of a prince; hears that the ladies of Nantes are making an addition to their heads in imitation of Franklin's hair cap, which they intend to call "a la Franklin."
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 25; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Departure of the Amphitrite. Letters received from M. Du Coudray, who has sent him seven officers and their baggage for the Mercury; number of officers he has been forced to refuse; encloses protest made by M. Du Coudray against the Captain of the Amphitrite. Difficulty of procuring charts of the American coast.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 26; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Jeanne. Saint Mal
    Concerning the relationship of herself and her son to Franklin; entreats his aid in their present distress and indigency.
    Printed in Hale's Franklin in France, I, 145.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 26; A.L. 1p.; Le Bègue Duportail, Louis. Paris
    He leaves for his home to arrange for his departure in a fortnight; has received the permits from the King for himself and his companions.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 27; A.N. in 3d P. 1p.; Paulze, Jacques. Paris
    Notifying him that the King's Library will be open for his visit on January 30th, and that the librarians will be prepard to receive him.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Jones, Capt. John Paul. Nantes
    Arrived from Paris in 56 hours; will give his best protection and safe conduct to the squadron now nearly ready to sail, until they are at some distance from the coast of Europe; this will afford him an opportunity to prove the sailing capacity of the Ranger, whereof he is in great suspense. Expediency of ordering prizes containing clothing, warlike or naval stores to America instead of to the European ports.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 27; A.L.S. 3p.; Vaughan, Benjamin. Essex
    Has decided to cancel the whole impression of Franklin's political works and wait for the additional pieces; has not yet received his remarks upon paper currency; advisability of having the American edition of Mr. Galloway's speech accompany the dialogue on slavery. All letters to and probably from England are opened. Expects Dr. Price's pamphlet out soon.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Briant de Peinquelein, François-Hyacinthe. Quimperlé
    Desires to serve in the American army; wishes to know what treatment he may expect from Congress; has served for six years as captain of Infantry. Does not wish to be confounded with those adventurers animated merely by sordid interest.
  - to The American Commissioners., 1777 January 27; A.L.S. 4p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Eleven officers claiming the right to take passage on the Mercury; cannot take but four; M. Du Coudray the most insistent; refusal of M. Peltier to take him; claims of the Chevalier de [la] Barre; finds his situation very disagreeable.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 27; A.L.S. 2p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Uncasy lest his adhering strictly to orders and refusing the officers will be misinterpreted.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 27; A.L.S. 1p.; Williams, Jonathan Jr.
    Proposes to send the Chevalier Mauduit Duplessis in the Mercury. Explains his reasons for speaking ill of Mr. P[eltier].
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 28; A.L.S. 7p.; Gallitzin, Dimitri, prince de. La Hague
    One of Franklin's most sincere admirers; his love of science his excuse for writing to him. Lays before him certain conclsions he has formed on the subject of electricity; begs to hear frankly whether he approves or disapproves of his ideas. His residence always at the Hague where he is the ambassador of the Empress of Russia.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 28; A.L S. 3p.; Montaudoüin de la Touche, Jean-Gabriel. Nantes
    Concerning the purchase and equipment of a ship bound for America. Surprised at seeing M. Du Coudray whom he imagined had sailed in the Amphitrite; causes of his return; hopes Franklin will see him at once; lack of circumspection on the part of the agent at Port Louis.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Buisson de Basseville, Pierre. Quimperlé
    Desirous of having a post in the service of America; was detained a prisoner for four years in England in the last war and has thereby acquired the English tongue.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 28; A.L.S. 1p.; Echlin, Henry. Prison of the Abbaye St. Germain
    According to Franklin's instruction, the bearer will wait to receive his orders. Begs him to return the list with whatever he is pleased to join to it.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 29; A.L.S. 4p.; Lee, Arthur. Bordeaux
    A letter received from London which says that ships are actually sent for the 10,000 Germans; that the English hope for great advantages from dissensions in Pennsylvania and that Burgoyne's destination is changed from Virginia to Boston. Cornwallis's defeat in New Jersey generally credited. Question of lightening the duties on exports and imports to and from the United States. A ship lying at Nantes is costing the Congress $100 freight per month; recommended her immediate sale, which Mr. Morris ought to have seen to long before. Mr. Myrecle's reputed character very bad. Repeated accusations made by the English that the Americans have wantonly hung some Hessian prisoners; thinks Congress should publish an authentic contradiction, that such an infamous imputation shall not go down to posterity. Badness of the roads; does not expect to reach his destination till March.
  - to Benjamin Franklin, 1777 January 29; A.L.S. 2p.; Ingenhousz, Jan
    Entrusted by the Emperor with the erection of conductors upon the gunpowder magazines and some other buildings; Venice has applied to the Emperor for aid in a like matter, and he has been asked to undertake the work. Thinks Father Beccaria is against the use of conductors; would like to prove him wrong. Will journey to Ratisbon about the 12th of April to inoculate the two sons of the reigning Prince of Tour and Taxis, after which would be glad to take a trip to Paris and enjoy Franklin's society.